Now at this point,
الآن، في هذه المرحلة
we know what is a project scope and what is a pricing framework.
نعرف معًا ما هو نطاق المشروع وما هو إطار التسعير.
In this important part of the lesson,
وفي هذا الجزء الهام من الدرس،
we'll talk about a correlation that exists between these two.
سنتحدث عن العلاقة القائمة بين هذين الأمرين.
It is important to understand how the scope and
ومن المهم فهم الكيفية التي يسير بها نطاق المشروع
the pricing framework of the project go hand in hand and are really interdependent.
وإطار التسعير جنبًا إلى جنب ليكونا مترابطين حقًا.
Let's say we're trying to determine the fixed cost;
لنقل أننا نحاول تحديد التكلفة الثابتة؛
the overall cost of a project that we want to charge the client.
التكلفة الإجمالية لمشروع نريد تحصيله للعميل.
When we do that, first,
عندما نفعل ذلك، أولًا،
we need to figure out what we're really trying to achieve here.
نحن بحاجة لمعرفة ما نحاول حقًا تحقيقه هنا.
What is our end goal?
ما هو هدفنا النهائي؟
For example, we might be trying to build a web application,
على سبيل المثال، قد نكون بصدد بناء تطبيق على شبكة الإنترنت،
or an Android application,
أو تطبيق أندرويد،
or a digital marketing solution,
أو حلول تسويق إلكتروني،
to increase traffic on the website.
أو زيادة الزيارات لموقع إلكتروني.
Now once we have determined what the end goal of the project is,
فبمجرد أن نحدد الهدف النهائي للمشروع،
we want to get in a little deeper and find out what exactly are
نريد أن نتعمق أكثر ونعرف بالضبط ما هي
the different features or tasks required to complete the project to achieve the goal.
النقاط أو المهام المختلفة المطلوبة لإنجاز المشروع لتحقيق الهدف.
For example, we may need an authentication module
على سبيل المثال، قد نحتاج إلى نموذج توثيق
as a feature of the web application or a social media campaign,
كأحد المتطلبات لشبكة الإنترنت أو لحملة منصات التواصل الاجتماعي،
maybe around the tasks,
فهذا قد يرتبط بالمهمة،
or work streams in a digital marketing solution.
أو تدفقات العمل في حلول التسويق الإلكتروني.
But we don't stop there.
ولكننا لا نتوقف عند ذلك.
To figure out how much we'd charge the client,
لنعرف كيف نحسب التكلفة التي يجب أن يدفعها العميل،
we need to go a little bit more deeper and
يجب أن نتعمق أكثر
draft a specification for each of these features.
ونضع مواصفات لكل متطلبات العمل.
For example, an authentication module may need
فنموذج التوثيق على سبيل المثال قد يحتاج
a forgot password feature in case the user forgets their password,
خاصية "نسيت كلمة المرور" في حال نسيان المستخدم لكلمة المرور،
a way to sign up new users,
طريقة لتسجيل المستخدمين الجدد،
keep the user session active for a fixed time.
إبقاء جلسة المستخدم نشطة لوقت محدد.
A social media campaign on the other hand may involve
ومن ناحية أخرى، قد تشمل الحملة على منصات التواصل الاجتماعي
further details like which platforms will the campaign be running on,
وتفاصيل أخرى مثل تحديد منصة التواصل التي سيتم عمل الحملة عليها،
how many posts per day will we be posting?
كم عدد المنشورات اليومية؟
Which define how much we need to prepare for these posts.
مما يساعدنا في معرفة ما نحتاجه لتحضير هذه المنشورات.
What kind of posts, image,
ما هي طبيعة المنشورات أو الصور
or text? How many contests?
أو النصوص؟ ما عدد المسابقات؟
What is the duration of the campaign?
ما هي المدة الزمنية للحملة؟
All of these details are really critical in figuring out
كل هذه الأمور هامة جدًا لتحديد
the total effort that we need to spend as a freelancer to work on that task.
المجهود المبذول الذي يقوم به الموظف الحر لإتمام المهمة.
Once we have the total effort,
بمجرد معرفة الجهد الإجمالي المبذول،
we can then estimate how much we want to charge the client for that much work.
نستطيع أن نحسب التكلفة التي يجب أن يدفعها العميل مقابل العمل.
Now let's say if we knew the goal,
لنفترض الآن أننا إذا عرفنا الهدف،
could we then estimate a fixed costs for the project?
هل يمكننا بعد ذلك تقدير التكاليف الثابتة للمشروع؟
We will not be able to do that since we do not know how
لن نكون قادرين على القيام بذلك لأننا لا نعرف
complex or sophisticated are the features that the client needs to fulfill the goal,
درجة تعقيد الميزات التي يحتاجها العميل لتحقيق الهدف،
which will define how much effort we spend on it.
وهذا سيحدد مقدار الجهد الذي ستبذله.
Could we do it if we have all the features,
هل يمكننا فعل ذلك إذا توفرت لدينا جميع الميزات،
but not the detailed specifications?
لكن بدون المواصفات التفصيلية؟
Still we won't be able to,
لن نتمكن من ذلك،
because the devil is in the details and the effort required for
لأن الجوهر يكمن في التفاصيل ويعتمد المجهود
each feature really depends on what goes in that feature,
المبذل في كل ميزة على ما تتضمنه هذه الميزة،
so we really need a detailed scope of the project.
لذلك نحتاج حقًا إلى نطاق تفصيلي للمشروع.
The detailed scope helps us determine the total effort that needs to be spent,
يساعدنا النطاق التفصيلي على تحديد الجهد الإجمالي الذي سيبذل،
which further determines the total cost of the project.
مما يحدد التكلفة الإجمالية للمشروع.
That is why the pricing structure is dependent on the scope of the project.
هذا هو السبب في أن هيكل التسعير يعتمد على نطاق المشروع.
If the scope is not defined in detail we will not be able to
إذا لم يتم تحديد النطاق بالتفصيل، فلن نتمكن من
come up with a fixed cost for the project end to end.
معرفة تكلفة ثابتة للمشروع من البداية إلى النهاية.